howdy this is jim rutt and this is the
jim rutt show
[Music]
listeners have asked us to provide
pointers to some of the resources we
talk about on the show
we now have links to books and articles
referenced in recent podcasts that are
available on our website
we also offer full transcripts go to
jimrutshow.com
that's jimrutsshow.com
today's guest is tyson yonkoporta hi jim
it's great to be back
hey yeah great to have you back uh for
our listeners this is part two we
recorded another episode about uh a week
ago
and the conversation got so dense and so
interesting we both agreed that hey we
couldn't do justice to the conversation
without doing a part two so here we are
with
part two a little background on tyson
he's an academic
an arts critic and a researcher who is a
member of the
appalachian clan in far northern
queensland
and for you people don't know about
australia that's kind of in the upper
right of australia i think if i got that
right
you know up as in uh north being top
which is of course
a very western way of thinking about the
world
sometimes you want to look at the map
the other other way around anyway
right that's where he comes from not
only does he do all this
kind of academic stuff but he also
carves traditional tools which we'll
talk about and weapons and also works as
a lecturer in indigenous
knowledge at deakin university in
melbourne he lives in melbourne
as in part one we're going to at least
loosely
root the discussion around uh tyson's
new book
called sand talk and i gotta tell you
this
is about the most interesting book
i've read in a couple of years with
respect to trying to understand
where we should go as a society i've now
finished reading the book about 10 days
ago and i read it carefully annotated it
and have been thinking about it i would
even say i have been
marinating myself in it for the last 10
days
and this is an odd feeling but i can
feel it almost in my dna
now that it's trying to speak to me and
tell me something
that i have never known and i've been
working on this thing called game b
with some friends and associates of mine
for several years we're trying to think
about
how to build a society for the west that
can actually endure
not self-terminate and can provide a way
better
quality of life for people and an
ethical way of living
and it's really hard to get there from
western civilization
tell you the truth and this book is
calling to me
the clouds haven't cleared i don't see
the beautiful horizon
but i truly feel that what tyson's
talking about here
is drawing me forward to how we really
think about transitioning
from western civilization which is on a
death spiral frankly
to something that's both sustainable and
wonderful
and i really can't put my finger on it
any more precisely than that
yeah you go forward into more clouds
that
there's just more clouds i haven't seen
that beautiful horizon
yet yeah i think it's there god damn it
i mean that's my hope
yeah it's got to be there but it's not
easy i'm telling you people
read this goddamn book this book will
change how you think
if you take it seriously and it it is
really a serious
book it will do amazing things to your
head so just read the goddamn book
all right so there we go
it is just uh it's a neural adventure
isn't it
it really is and it sticks with you yeah
i mean you know the damn thing dwell
i just dwell on it i really do and i go
back and think about the examples you
give
which are from all over the place i mean
talk about multi-perspective i mean
you know the book uses complexity
science as a strong lens
i think as we talked about last time the
book has complexity
or complex 77 times in it i'm a bit of a
quant nerd on text i have some tools let
me analyze it
and yet it also looks back from you know
at least 50 000 years
of history from the uh indigenous
uh australian perspective and it's quite
interesting how the two perspectives
often provide the same answer which is
just uncanny tell you it's true
as i said last time all your transcripts
together would probably have at least 76
in it
as well oh way more than that way more
i think i got at least one that probably
has that media add a zero to that
yeah exactly and and and that's despite
the fact that
i have so far as chewed talking about
game a politics on the show
yeah if i ever do that i'll definitely
break 76 in the uh
you know in the first episode yeah yeah
it's it's funny that
it never comes in with the talk about
hard forks and the dunbar number
you know they talk about all your
defectors and you this and that but they
they never quite get down to the
politics and the polarization that
happens
and that's by design frankly that you
know in our game b conversations and a
lot of
and what i do on my podcast i want to
get beyond
all that team red team blue at least in
the us
vernacular yeah because they're both
wrong right
the real answer is not even close to
either one
so why should we deplete our emotional
energy lining up in teams and fighting
over
what's not even close to their way
forward so
that's my perspective on it and that's
why i resist the temptation at least
with my game a hat on i mean i gained b
hat on
to be dragged into those conversations
now with my game b hat anyone who
follows me on facebook
knows that i uh a bash a certain
stupid-ass incumbent in the united
states on a regular basis but we're not
going to talk about that today aren't
no all right no but i do want one of
those game b hats do you have a merch
thing happening you need to get a store
up yeah we do we don't have one yet i
mean
you know and the issue is there is no
game b organization it's you know
radically decentralized of course that
means anyone who wants to could set up a
store
but there is no official game be
anything which is part of its charm
anyway before we uh get back into the
details of the book
i'd love to have you chat a little bit
about uh a theme that comes in
every chapter and which is the wooden
artifacts of various sorts that you make
and i also do a little woodworking i'm
sure not nearly as cool as yours
tell me a little bit about you and
woodworking and why it was important to
you
to spend a you know a fair amount of
time talking about the woodworking you
did
while you were writing each chapter yeah
well the the woodworking is the center
of my
like uh cognitive process and my
cognitive world and
and also uh so describing
that that web of relations of neural
relations around
that that explains better this idea of
what the mind is
and what my theory of mind is because
that's
that's how i do all my my cognitive work
is through that you know i mean i've got
to cut different kinds of woods
for different kinds of implements from
different many different places
in exactly the right season you know or
it'll go wrong
and i've got to have an association with
that plant that species as well um and i
have to understand the story
and where that story goes like a map in
the land
so songs these song lines through the
landscape we talked about
that is like a big cognitive map of the
landscape
so you have these inner landscapes as
well you know in your mind and you're
traveling them
and connecting up all these stories and
eventually they web
all the way across the continent just
intersecting
so you're sitting right at the middle of
this you know so some other thing i
think i describe
in one that i've made two boomerangs
that are split
from the same tree yeah it was a
beefwood tree
and i can't pick those up without sort
of almost being in that place
and no matter how far apart those
boomerangs are they're still connected
it's that uh what do they call that in
quantum physics when you've got those
two particles
entanglement entanglement i'm doing like
boomerang entanglement yeah
but everything's entangled you know so
the place where i cut those is 3 000
kilometers away from where i am now
and i'm still entangled with that place
and you know if i pick them up
those boomerangs if i pick them up i'm
going to pick them up now and see what
happens but yeah if i'm
holding them in my hands
it's i just go into a different place so
i'm there
you know and i'm standing and i can see
the tree
ah yeah and when i
uh clap those together it's it kind of
really animates them and animates my
mind
and takes me to that place and i can see
the tree the beef wood tree it's got
these little
sort of these split hard nuts that you
can use as clothes pegs
um there's a nut inside there that you
can eat as well
that's medicinal it smells like uh
it smells amazing the wood you know it's
gonna do you good
so it's got a lot of different
properties this tree but i'm looking
right out and
you know across it's just up from a
swamp area like a tea tree swamp
and of course straighter then away then
i think you know mother side
has a totemic connection to those tea
trees
but then that swamps like a scary place
there's like um
people you know if people are doing
sorcery they'll sneak off there and do
that kind of thing so you gotta be
careful there
and then there's these uh two brothers
these yochiyochi
these sort of weird spirit things that
that sort of sneak around in the swamp
there as well so there's that story
and it just goes on and on but then i
see the imbalances
so there's termite mounds there but the
termite mounds are oversized
and they look beautiful and you know
tourists take photos of them but it's
breaks my heart because i can see that
that means the place is sick
because when the termite mounds get too
big you know it's out of balance
and i know that the golden shoulder
parrot that used to nest in there is
extinct now
just in the last couple of decades
you know and it's extinct because um
there's a moth there used to be a moth
that's gone now
that lays its eggs in the nest
of the golden shoulder parrot that has
its nest inside the turmoil
termite mound because it's a perfectly
regulated temperature in there
and then the moth eggs and the bird eggs
hatch at the same time
and so as the birds are growing up the
larvae is eating
the of those baby birds if that's
not happening then the baby birds just
drown in their own in that hole in
the termite nest and so that's what's
happened
and they lived for you know 50 years or
something
so nobody really noticed and then all of
a sudden
those parrots were gone and then there's
an imbalance there and
everything's going wrong and and so the
whole place gets sick and the termite
mounds are getting
you know oversized and everything's
going wrong
you know and then there's a tree nearby
that
it's supposed to get red flowers on it
you know in a particular season and when
the red flowers come you know that it's
time to get
and go and collect oysters because that
that means the oysters are fat
and that sure those trees haven't
flowered for about five years
and the oysters haven't been getting fat
for about five years
you know everything's going really wrong
there there's um
you know a lot of bauxite mining
happening there and
you know there's a lot of imbalances and
people sort of look at it like untouched
wilderness but you can see that it's
dying you know
yeah very interesting and that's one of
the things i noticed throughout the book
is that when you have when you're using
the indigenous lens
the knowledge is connected
to physical representations i mean if we
use the western
terminology you could say they're
mnemonics but i suspect it's actually
a lot deeper than that yeah also when
i'm composing like always before i write
something i'll carve something first
and i'll cover it in it's it's a haptic
cognition act
you know you have that haptic cognition
where the tool is the extension
of your arm and then the other tool that
you're making
your knowledge the things you're
thinking through and the things you're
composing
are going into that wood as you carve it
you know and then you go one step
further and actually etch those designs
into the wood as well
as a further mnemonic thing it's adding
another visual
layer to it so you know all the entire
book
is a you know i'm looking at a pile of
tools there now that's the actual book
and that would be like more than karl
marx there's a lot of volumes there you
know
so the you know the books and talk
itself i'm just translating fragments
from each of those tools into that
uh but there's a lot more to it as well
yeah so it's this
uh with this cognition there are
terabytes of information there and
they're in this landscape these
maps you carry around you know because
memory is
navigational you know cognitively
speaking
navigation and story are the two main
main tools we use as human beings for
memory
and so we have that mnemonic of the the
sky the sky is reflecting the land so
the night sky is also a map of the
landscape
wherever you are and as the stars move
around they tell you different stories
of what's happening in different seasons
in the landscape you know so you get
those cycles of time happening there
and so you've got those maps reflecting
each other so there's terabytes of
knowledge that are recorded
in the stars as well you know so that's
a vast
infinite text yeah i love that so you
know i i guess if you if you're talking
about if you're trying to put together
ideas about you know an ideal society
and you're basing this in evolutionary
theory
and you're postulating things about well
what cavemen did
it's worth consulting or looking at the
complexity of paleolithic cultures and
the cognition
within paleolithic cultures are still
existing cultures
looking at those to look at the kind of
complexity you got there because if
you're just imagining
a modern human dropped back in that
context
then all you're going to get is flight
or fight and
the fittest survive and all that kind of
weirdness
and and so you're going to end up with a
flawed model right from the start
yeah that's again that's what i was
talking about the dna calling to me that
there is something deeper and richer
than anything we've experienced in our
western at least my i shouldn't speak
for you because you've experienced both
in my western kind of flat culture right
and it's a known fact from physical
anthropology
that the civilized man's brain is
actually smaller
by about 10 percent than the earlier
man those still modern humans brain say
from 30 or 40
000 years ago including in you know most
this research was in europe the
so-called cro-magnon man
because our lives were way more complex
than it was
hard you talk a bit about the snowman
who was found up in
the alps right oh yeah the iceman yeah
the iceman the iceman and
wow you know considering that they had
very minimal technologies that the day
the iceman was astoundingly well
prepared for life in an extreme
environment
he was but he was kind of on that cusp
and he was very
very sick like already sort of poisoned
from this
emerging industrial and agricultural
culture that he was involved with a lot
of evidence there so he he was
full of arsenic from the bronze forge
you know because he'd obviously been
forging weapons at a at a forge and
that that was a highly toxic process
that it poisoned him horribly he was
riddled with arsenic he also had lyme
disease
you know lyme disease tells me that
while they were probably still doing a
bit of hunting and gathering
they'd stop caring for their land
properly the ticks that you get they
they're not out of control if you're
looking after the the country properly
if you're looking after the land
yeah if you have birds on the land yeah
ground birds will take care of your tick
problem
and even like you know burning off areas
if they're too scrubby
and that there's too much fuel load if
for some reason
like perhaps you've come into that place
and displaced some of the mega fauna
that usually eats that
then you don't want to let that fuel
load build up
because for a start you end up with you
know
massive bushfires in greenland or
whatever
that you know we had earlier this year i
mean yeah
like once you get rid of the mega fauna
you you really like the really big mega
fauna then you really do need to be
taking care of that fuel load and
burning off
uh and that'll also take care of your
ticks
that's a good point it's an interesting
little just an aside i don't know you
probably know this you know everything
about
it seems like in this area but when we
look at the energy consumption
of uh societies in general they've been
increasing
over time until finally they're
extremely high
at the you know advanced civilization
so-called
but the aboriginal people are actually
an exception that rule
if you include the use of fire to
control the land
the aboriginal people were almost as
high as western civilization
in terms of the amount of energy that
they used
yeah i mean that and ah so many things
that so many um
just symbioses that you you put yourself
in that interactive action with the
landscape when you belong to it
you know when you're part of it like i i
don't think there's anybody
so in in my family's community there's
you know
everyone's always in the river and it's
full of crocodiles but
i i've never ever heard of someone being
taken by a crocodile
you know and i mean until very recently
until about the 1950s the custom was to
take the haircut
of of a male child the first haircut
they had as
a baby and do that and you'd cut that
hair
in that uh crocodile nesting season
so then you catch a baby crocodile and
you tie the hair around the baby
crocodile's head
and let it go and the same way you're
talking about feeling changes in your
dna
that would make a an entanglement i
guess
a kind of if not quantum then molecular
entanglement between
that man as he grew and that crocodile
as he grew
and that would be that man's crocodile
and he could go down to the river and
call the crocodile and he'd come up
and so that man could go swimming in the
river and wouldn't have to worry about
sharks crocodiles anything else that
crocodile would help him
and they would hunt together and i know
that sounds like an apocryphal tale
but there are photos of this still all
around the world because um
the missionaries they used to get
international tourists coming there
and then they'd get all the men in the
town to run down to the river and
call their crocodiles and jump in and
hold up the crocodiles tails in the
river and all the tourists would take
photos so that's something that
definitely happened
although it doesn't happen anymore which
is a shame really
yeah it's a that that shows how closely
integrated your people were with the
land
they could see the patterns right and
they did their rituals
to reinforce those patterns yeah and so
hunting with a crocodile takes a lot
less energy if you know what i mean
you know if you're catching very big
fish that are about the size of a 10
year old child
with your crocodile companion it makes
hunting a lot easier
there's there's a lot of things like
that that have just been they seem like
you know superhero powers now those are
the things you need to survive in a
tough environment for you know tens of
thousands of years in equilibrium with
your environment
yeah but then also if that environment
is incredibly abundant
and you're managing it properly then it
isn't a harsh environment i mean it's a
harsh environment to try and survive in
now because
you know 50 of everything's dead in it
so it is
quite hard to um scrape together enough
food
out there you know it is harsh to try
and survive there now
but you know back in the day it was
incredibly abundant
and you only needed to do about two
hours of work a day and then that was
that was it the rest was for um
the important things in life yeah that's
that's something we'll get to a little
later that that issue
yeah why the hell are we working so hard
on things that are like just
total right yeah but first i
want to jump back
into some actual words from your book
which i think tee up
the discussion in an interesting way and
this overlaps a bit with our discussion
from last time in a little bit more
general terms and this
is uh emu is a troublemaker who brings
into
being the most destructive idea in
existence
i am greater than you you are less than
me
this is the source of all human misery
aboriginal society has designed over
thousands of years to deal with this
problem
some people are just idiots and everyone
has a bit of idiot in them from time to
time coming from some deep place inside
that whispers
you are special you are greater than
other people and things
you are more important than everything
and everyone all things and all people
exist to serve you
this behavior needs massive checks and
balances
to contain the damage it can do
containing the excesses of malignant
narcissists
is a team effort
well i mean the entire australian
aboriginal society
basically was designed over millennia to
deal with that problem
and i think in any you know game b
kind community really that's what you
have to deal with first
you have to design everything around
so everything from your social norms you
know
uh to your just different cultural
expressions to your rules
to your kinship to all your structures
your institutions
everything has to be designed to check
narcissism even the language you speak
everything has got to be
holding that in check and it's got to be
punishing it harshly as soon as it
appears
but not punishing it in a nasty way but
in a
a way that's designed to transform you
the transgressor and everybody else
that's involved in the punishment as
well
everybody learns everybody transforms we
discussed that uh
yeah that sort of criminology of that
last time we did go into the criminology
stuff last time
narcissism is the thing you know it is
that
uh that seed and you know that the emu
story
you know at the start of creation all
the stories talk about that emu
and and he's often or she as well
is uh is often you know that one who's
making that mess that first one who has
that
that i'm look at me look at me i'm the
best
you know i should be the boss of
everybody you know so it's that first
injunction against people seeking to be
the boss or to place themselves over
and what blows me away is that you know
the traditional symbol
you know the sand torque symbol so you
know what you draw in the sand or
or paint on on the rock wall or whatever
uh the symbol for that is
is exactly the same as the mathematical
greater than
sign that's quite interesting it's just
uh yeah i just uh thought that was an
amazing little
uh congruence happening there you know
that the mathematical greater than sign
is also the sign for this this being who
you know invented that first malicious
thought that's the source of all human
misery
and that goes all the way back you know
one of my favorite books people listen
to podcasts have heard me mention it
before but it makes exactly the same
point about other cultures called
hierarchy in the forest
the evolution of egalitarian behavior by
chris
bowen yeah and he does an amazing job of
looking at numerous forager societies
pre-agricultural societies
and he discovers something very
interesting that
all of them that survive any length of
time and he admits that probably a bunch
didn't developed cultural methods to
suppress
big men basically and he also then looks
at the
genetic record and behaviors of our
chimp and bonabeau ancestors both of
whom
are way more hierarchical than humans
are
at their hunter gatherer at the forager
stages and
he essentially argues that forager level
civilization was principally about
bringing down people who thought they
were greater than everybody else
yeah and that that's a worldwide pattern
for all societies that existed for any
extended period of time
but then at the same time so in our
cultures you do provide for that because
sometimes you have emergent situations
or projects that come out that demand
some kind of a hierarchy
temporary hierarchy yeah we talk about
that in the game b world word we use i'd
love to hear
how it really how it relates to the
language that your people use
we distinguish between role-based
leadership
and position-based leadership yeah
position-based leadership is
hey i'm the manager of the butt
department or something and i organize
all the butt over all time
whether i know anything about butt
or not right
while uh role based leadership would be
hmm
you know we're going on a difficult hunt
against a mammoth here
and tyson is the biggest baddest
mammoth hunter in the group and knows
the most about it somebody's gotta butt
that mammoth
exactly and tyson's the only guy crazy
enough to do it
[Laughter]
that's role based leadership yeah and
when the butt is done
he's no longer the leader he had he had
he was the band for the job so
uh by acclimation uh he's the leader we
all listen to until the job's done
yeah it's it's all contextual so i mean
everything's contextual in our culture
it's like the dynamic subordination are
you talking about and you know the navy
seals do it
and they have to do it in an instant you
know no matter how many stripes you've
got on your shoulder back on the ship
you know when you're in action
you need to be able to change you know
as the terrain changes as the weather
changes you know like you know it might
start snowing and then so suddenly well
jim you're you take point you
will listen to you because you're the
snowscape dude
and that's the way it goes you know
you've got to be able to switch in the
moment
particularly because i was telling you
about that sort of
those kind of maps of the landscape you
know everybody has a role for
speaking for different parts of that
landscape within your territory
you know so each family has places there
so a side of the river that
that they speak for and that people uh
will need to ask their permission if
they want to do things there
or they will need to defer to that
person you know when you're moving
through that part of the river
but you might be on the other side of
the river and that's well that's your
uncle's
side there so you know you defer to him
and if he's not there
then everybody in the group is going to
defer to you because he's your uncle
and so you're inheriting that place from
him so you speak
for that place and you know people will
have to follow you
but then you move around the river bend
and you go up the hill well who speaks
for those hills who has that story
and so on and so forth so as you move
across the landscape
you're constantly shifting in your
leadership roles
dynamic subordination it's all drawn
back to the
physical and again that's such a
interesting and different way of
of organizing the collective knowledge
yeah the other other thing i want to
probe into a little bit about collective
knowledge is you
many times reference uh your
interactions with elders
and you even confess that you know due
to your own personal autobiography you
were never
never went through the manhood rituals
so in terms of
hierarchy in the elderness not really
hierarchy it's a different kind of
relationship i'd love you to talk about
that
you're still a 13 year old kid right
yeah and so what is an
elder and how does how does that
elderhood
work and how would you distinguish it
between
western style position based leadership
or you know the boss of the buttfuckers
that
organizes all the butt even you
don't know anything about it right yeah
well it's it's funny because that that
elderhood
you know we've kind of taken that on
board but it's kind of something that's
been
mapped over you know most cultures that
have been uh colonized
so you'll see it in india you'll see it
you know even with your
african slave descendants you know in
america
all that sort of stuff you know they
always call uncle tom or aunty this
and it's the same in in india there's
this kind of this idea of elderhood
that's western that's been imposed on
the top and a lot of people have
started sort of have really internalized
that model but it is a lot more dynamic
than that like you don't just become an
elder when you reach a certain age and
wait
um because you know that would just be
positional authority again you know you
don't do that
you know the people who have shown that
they have that discipline
that they can suppress their narcissism
and really
reach those higher levels of knowledge
and you know knowledge is our capital
you know and you don't get to accumulate
it unless you pass every
test along the way there's also
positional things so
i'm a younger sibling and so that's my
older brother he's the one who speaks
for all that knowledge and
and i don't speak for that as a younger
sibling uh also as somebody who hasn't
been initiated
you know that that makes uh things
different as well especially when i go
around
with other groups but most people you
know a lot of people my age and younger
most are not initiated now anyway
because that's not happening anymore now
why not i mean i
when we think about game b one of the
things that we're softly specifying in
what comes next is there needs to be
these initiations particularly on that
step from adulthood
yeah and it probably ought to be a hell
of a lot younger than 21 or 18 even
well looking for most of the continent
that it stopped happening because you
you get shot or whipped or you'd have
your children taken away
or you'd be uh thrown in a truck and
moved to the other side of the continent
if you participated in any cultural
rituals of that kind
you know so they were illegal for a long
time right up until you know very
recently
so for a lot of people it was because of
that but for my family's community
that's a swimming pool was built
on the initiation ground a few decades
ago
so yes that that that was it and that's
the first stage initiation right there
so as soon as that was built there that
that was that tradition was finished
that's too bad so no young men can go
through those uh
those ceremonies anymore but it's it's
sort of shifted we adapt
now it's um jail is the right of passage
uh for young men
you know um you go to jail and strangely
enough when you're in jail you learn a
lot of cultural
things you know there's workshops and
you you learn to do indigenous art and
you
you do lots of dancing and all that sort
of thing and um
you you know learn other criminal sort
of activities and become a bit of a
gangster and then
then you're unleashed back into the
world so that's the right of passage
now uh for a lot of men it doesn't
sound like it's necessarily the the best
yeah it's not the best but you adapt to
you know use whatever you've got what's
available to you i guess
but uh yeah so there are you know
it's not really a hierarchy it's just
that you you
there's a lot of secret and very sacred
knowledge
that can't just be thrown around for
anybody you know so you have keepers of
that knowledge you only
earn the right to keep that knowledge
through being very dedicated throughout
their life
uh towards that and you know you have to
go through different stages of
initiation every 15 years
to get the next layer it's like you know
getting your um
high school diploma and then getting
your you know your bachelor degree and
then
then doing your honors and then or a
master's and then doing a doctorate and
then doing post doctorate work
it's pretty much the same as that if you
don't have the tools to take on that
knowledge
or the right personality traits then
you're not going to get it
but then it doesn't matter if you don't
get it anyway because you're still a
highly valued member of the
group anyway nobody's above you and no
one's below you
because you're not special and that's
what you learn in that first initiation
which i've been i've gone through the
early stages of that now
yeah in i had to go to another place to
start doing that
but yeah what what you come out from
that with is a
strong sense that you are not special
but then at the same time nobody else is
that special either
you know but that you all belong to
something special yeah
damn near the center of the issue
in fact another quote from the book is
perhaps the transferable wisdom here is
simply that most young men need
something a little meatier
than mindfulness workshops to curtail
the terrifying narcissism
that overtakes them from the moment
their balls
drop absolutely every male at
13 14 maybe even 12
uh you know pretty much needs to be
isolated
into a very different group of people
and should not
be emerging until they're
18 19 or something like that
yeah some of the most destructive people
on the planet
uh 15 year old boys some of the most
interesting too right i like
i always said if i ever were to teach
school i would take on
you know eighth graders uh or ninth
graders you know
14 13 14 15 years old you know
there's something real about them right
yeah at least there was
you know from what they're trying to do
to kids in our american schools at least
they're
you know they're they're trying to break
them right you can't do anything anymore
you call the police if you get into a
little fist fight what the
right yeah that's it that's another
quote in the book is if you want to find
the next generation of great thinkers
you look in the detention room of any
high school
yeah that's right yeah that's right you
always think of that life as
sweaty and meaty real life right yeah
and of course it pisses off the powers
that be and then sort of finish up on
this idea of
i am greater than you you tie that back
to a christian
myth and you call it the luciferian lie
you know again lucifer satan yeah at
least
in the later stories uh that are told
there's a little bit in the bible but a
lot of it was stuff written in the
in medieval times that allegedly uh
you know satan came about when the
greatest angel rebelled against god
saying that i'm greater than you yeah
it's just
and then and then he fell as and there's
always this idea of the fall of man
and every culture has its its mythology
around that
you know even cain and abel that was
about that you know with
the first people and i guess even the
original sin
garden of eden all that sort of thing um
all these things are always about that
moment
of narcissism of thinking that you can
be
greater than you are and greater than
you know um other things around you that
you could have knowledge over
dominion over um all these kinds of
things
now there's an interesting part of cain
and abel that most people didn't notice
in the story
abel was a herdsman of sheep
while kane was a dirt farmer yeah and
that interesting
yeah that's it too yeah very few people
noticed that
in the story yeah well you know
pastoralism is
sustainable with that kind of thing you
know shepherds and flocks um
you know maintaining grasslands in
perpetuity like that it's um
yeah pastoralism is is a way of life
that can be sustainable
but yeah that intensive agriculture
that's um
that's always been a bad idea and one of
the problems of course is it locks you
into owning a particular parcel of land
this is
mine right and my my square of land is
greater than yours so we get back to
this
greater than issue again yeah yeah
although it is possible there are people
there are societies that have organized
the use of land in a much more commons
oriented approach and i think do you
think that's a
an approach that's worth thinking about
in the future is how can we become
commoners on the land even if we are
still stuck doing agriculture for a
while because of the number of people
that we have
ah the penny just dropped on the origin
possibly of the word commoners
you know aristocrats used to refer to
peasants as commoners didn't they
they did they did yeah and maybe it's
because they were
working the comments ah i had not
thought about that is a very interesting
thought i'm gonna follow up on that
after the
after the show and see if those two can
uh can get together i recently did a
podcast i think it'll be out on monday
maybe
with michelle bauwens of the p2p
foundation
and he is one of the biggest promoters
of the idea of the commons and that the
commons
is what we have lost and what we need to
regain and i think that's going to be
part
part of thinking about what comes next
may not be the only way yes we live in a
more complicated and complex world we'll
get to the distinction between
complicated and complex here in a minute
or two because it's way too complicated
there's somewhere in melbourne we walked
past the other day and we saw that it
was a
commons that you know community had set
up behind a big fence with um
chains and padlocks on it and it just
looked beautiful in there and so we're
walking along with the kids and we're ah
can we come in and have a look at this
no they wouldn't let us in
so well you know i think right there
your comments are not commons
and what you created is a closed system
you bastards and we know what happens in
closed
systems yeah entropy yeah i hope your
zucchinis fall off the bloody vine
second law thermodynamics yeah yeah
yeah in a book with a lot of this on
your comments you
that should be a warning to people who
think that they're commenters right if
your systems aren't open
in fact you know eleanor ostrom does
talk about that you know the systems
have to be open
but on the other hand and this will come
back to the management of the commons
you know my argument is you have to have
a semi-permeable membrane
right the people who have the commons
have to allow things in and out
yeah but they need to have you know make
some socially informed decisions
about what passes through right you know
for instance
no sociopaths would be my rule inside my
commons
and that we'd have some means to keep
them out
because if you don't the raider is going
to come and steal your zucchini
whether they're healthy or not you know
attempt to say all is
fully open to all is probably not
correct i mean that's not how any
complex system works any complex system
that manages to get any
real level of complexity has membranes
around it but they're not closed and
closed as you as you point out quite
brilliantly uh then the second law of
thermal dynamics rules and basically
it's just headed for the ship pile
either sooner or later but if you're
open
you exchange energy and material with
the outside world and information yeah
and so long as the outside world has
fluxes of energy and matter that are way
larger than your container uh then you
can go on inside your container forever
yeah that's it but um i don't know you
might utilize your sociopaths too
there's another thing i mean they've got
to have some
useful and generalizable skills you know
so i mean they can
do all the butchering for example so as
long as you because they have that
special gift where they can gut
something without
even their heart rate going up you know
so that's pretty good you so you've got
someone in in the community who's not
gonna
you know be being traumatized by by
having to butcher an animal
so you get them to do that work and then
i guess if a
true psychopath comes through then you
send your sociopath after them
they say we're gonna need you to take
that guy out
yeah and then they'd feel they'd feel
highly valued
for their sociopathy and um and they
might be content
with that you just don't let them near
the kids yeah that is that's interesting
that is one of the arguments actually
you know sociopathy seems to be about
one percent of the population
worldwide in most cultures and the one
the argument is why has it uh
lasted and the answer is it does have
some utility perhaps in war i hadn't
thought of the one about
dealing with otherwise uh emotionally
disturbing work like
slaughter though i've slaughtered so
damn many deer over the years that i got
over my squeamishness probably about
number five or six something like that
but certainly initially it was it took a
lot of emotional energy to get yourself
to do it but
yeah yeah and probably a sociopath would
be better at that yeah well you'd you'd
want him on the walls you know like
he's a sociopath sure but he's our
sociopath
of course one of the disturbing things
about western civ which i talk about
regularly on the show
is that if you know probably only one
percent of people in the west are
sociopaths
maybe a little more because of the
upness of our way of life
but in positions of authority it's way
higher than that
my estimate having played at pretty high
levels in corporate america
on wall street and even in the white
house when i was young
is that sort of the c-level suites in
corporate america i'd say 10
of those people are sociopaths yeah it's
really dangerous to let sociopathy
get control of levers in role-based
leadership
i mean not role-based in position-based
leadership yeah that's why you have to
have checks and balances throughout your
culture throughout your language
throughout all your institutions
all at every level you've got to have
those checks and balances
and that's like i said the team effort
and as you said
earlier we talked about a little bit in
passing but i just remembered it
from the book is that the elders one of
their
superpowers that they develop is to
detect narcissistic behavior
in people and to refuse to deal with
them
while they're showing the narcissistic
behavior yeah that's it
now frustrating for a sociopath if they
can't
gain access to the the social goods to
the
to the capital of your your culture
which is knowledge
you know and and because you know
sociopaths always want to do well they
always want to rise
so you know they're going to have to
really hold that in check if they ever
want to have access to that knowledge
you know otherwise they're just um no
sociopath wants to be a child forever
indeed that basically highlights a
potential control mechanism all right
we have our sociopaths at one percent
and they have some utility but how do we
keep them away from the lovers of power
maybe one of the ways is that those who
hold the wisdom
refuse to pass it on yeah when they
detect sociopathy yeah
or they pass on a special useful for
sociopaths
and also just make sure that there are
many many levels of power and they're
widely distributed throughout the group
and that they're transient you know i
would argue yeah
transient yeah you know you know as you
said you're on a journey and you're in
your uncle's
area for a part of it and you're in your
grandfather's
area for another part of it and then
you're out in the part where nobody has
geographic authority and you know so
so it's not one one boss all the time
that starts to dominate people
well let's see what do we talk about
next one later in my notes but let's
just talk about it now because
i think it's related and this is what
you talk about in the book and that
people in the area of complexity applied
complexity talk about a fair amount
which is the distinction between complex
and complicated
yeah um and and i've i've heard a lot of
i mean even just on your show i've heard
different people coming on
with completely opposite views of which
is which
you know i've heard some people describe
complexity as complicated
and complicated as complex you know and
i've heard you describe it as the
difference between the dancer and the
dance
well now that's between i would call
that is between reductionism and
complexity right
right a little different yeah the dancer
is what you get from reductionism and
the dance is complex
yeah well to me complicated is a system
that is tinkered
and that needs to be constantly tinkered
with
upgraded you know mended you know that
it it doesn't have that that auto poesis
going on
it can't heal itself it can't go through
periods of
you know homeostasis and hysteresis that
it's just you know it's like this this
computer that we couldn't get to work at
the start of the interview
but that's i mean once it's stuffed it's
stuffed that's it
not like a boomerang that if it's not
shaped quite right you can
file it down a little bit until it is
it's not going to heal itself it's just
you know we just had to turn it off and
turn it back on again
and i'm going to have to take it in you
know to the shop now and get it fixed
because it's playing up you know so
they're going to have to update
it and they're going to have to you know
do all the other tinkering things that
they need to do with
all the ones and zeros to make it run
properly and you know to me that's
that's a complicated
thing yeah yeah i think that's exactly
right an example i use for complicated
versus complex
i can actually have two i'd love to get
your reaction to it one
is a classic complicated system is an
industrial farm
you know that involves pesticides
herbicides fertilizers tractors you know
hiring
armies of pickers in the picking season
that you pay for with cash
you know taxes that you have to pay bank
loans etc
like your computers an intricate system
and if any one part fails significantly
you're
right as compared to let's say a
woodlands
you know where my farm is for instance
until the chestnut blight came in the
1930s brought from
uh elsewhere these lands were amazingly
rich in chestnuts 50
of the trees were huge chestnut trees
chestnuts are very rich in fatty nuts
yeah and they'd fall to the ground every
fall and they would be this amazing food
for the deer and even we had
bison and elk in this eastern area prior
to
western agriculture appearing and there
are other food sources as well
there's acorns that's the second biggest
crop and there's several different kinds
on
even today on our farm we have 10
different kinds of oak trees
and some years the white oaks produce
real well other years the red oaks some
years the black oaks some here's the
chestnut oaks
and so there's no one solid failure mode
it's a robust
system and you have big game like deer
and bear we still have both
then you have smaller game like rabbits
and uh
groundhogs and you know in a pinch you
could live off the rabbits in the ground
awesome
and the squirrels that for some reason
well the pigs uh the pigs must like that
too
uh fortunately we don't have wild pigs
here yet yeah they tear the out of
things yeah but
and during settler time uh one of the
interesting things we did have a commons
and it was
in fact we still have the legal basis
for it our counties what's called a
fence out
county which means if you don't want
somebody else's animals on your land
it's your obligation to put up a fence
to keep them out okay
and people are still in theory allowed
to let their animals wander
and so in settler times they used to let
the pigs out into this chestnut forests
in the every fall
and then they'd have to go round them up
you know a couple of weeks later and
they'd be big and fat let me tell you
after
doing nothing but gorging on chestnuts
for two or three weeks
but anyway so the distinction between
you know mature forest on one side
and industrial agriculture on the other
is to my mind a classic uh
distinction between complicated being
the industrial farm and complex being a
natural
mature forest yeah and you know the
the complicated just can't be sustained
you know there's this just this
obsolescence
in it that you know can't be denied i
guess it comes back to that entropy
thing again
yeah i used to stand um at a place it
was on a table land
and there was a road there you could
stand on the road and you could look on
one side
where the people who owned that they'd
cut down every single tree
so that it was just pasture because they
wanted to maximize the pasture
and it was a very very thin pasture with
some very skinny sick looking sheep on
it
you know and it was like a dust bowl
there it was just dead
and dry and then on the other side of
the road
they'd left the trees in so you had very
big old growth trees there
and the pasture was magnificent you know
because the trees are doing things there
that bringing up and sharing nutrients
they're breaking up the rocks you know
down deep
and and bringing up phosphorus and all
kinds of things you know so the soil on
one side of the road was beautiful and
the pasture was very rich
and the sheep were very fat and then on
the other side of the road the sheep
were sick and dying
because of the tinker complicated bloody
system they put there and you know
they're always out there
spraying super phosphate you know around
trying to coax some more life out of the
dead ground
but yeah that ground was finished yeah
it's uh
very unfortunate what we've done with
our soils uh
under cultivation and it's been
accelerating very very rapidly since
about 1950
uh with exactly things you're talking
about in the glyphosates which
produce for a while high productivity
because you get rid of the weeds but
unfortunately you kill
the micro biome in the soil basically
the funguses
which is really where the energy gets
marshaled made available for other plant
life you know we don't use that stuff on
our farm and we have kept over 50
percent of the land in forests
beautiful uh you know for for just those
reasons and we have
when we do use fertilizer we use turkey
for fertilizer
nice from a turkey house nearby and it
provides
energy to the plants but it also
provides a tremendous boost to the
you know the microorganisms in the soil
and our you know we bought this place
had been abused and overgrazed and all
kinds of stuff for a hundred years
and there was no worms in the soil that
was a sign
of no health today you you put a shovel
to the soil
and unless it's during a drought you
pull up a one shovel full of soil and
you probably have 10 or 20
uh earthworms yeah that sounds good yeah
they're part of that cycle
it's very very important to say the
least
all right let's move on to another topic
which is
the idea of a custodial species again i
think this is one of these things that's
calling to me
that you know i don't quite understand
but saying there's something right about
this
in the book several times you talk about
the fact that
humans at least at the moment are the
custodial
species for the earth tell us about that
and what does that mean yeah well that
comes out
a lot of our old stories are from all
over
you know it's our purpose for being here
it's um
you know our emergence in this system
has been
uh because the system had need of a
custodial species
you know for its longevity but also to
maintain
increase within the system so um
increase as opposed to growth so not
growing the size of the system but
increasing the relatedness within the
system all of the
connectivity you know those those
infinite combinatorials you know we're
supposed to
oversee that and everything about
everything we do is supposed to work in
with that our culture everything else
it's not supposed to be something that's
separate from nature
there isn't even supposed to be a
separate concept for nature
because we are nature you know we occupy
a very important
ecological niche you know it's not an
apex niche or anything like that either
we have a very important ecological
niche we're supposed to be in this
habitat
and anywhere where we're not there you
might think of it as untouched
wilderness but that place will be dying
because it needs us there
those trees have evolved over a long
time
to even just need our urine if you're
not pissing on the ground
in those places those plants will be
suffering over time and you'll you'll
see
die back in places and wonder why is
that
why is there die back happening there
and i'm looking at and thinking well
that needs
you know a couple of decades of people
pissing their on those trees
to make that place work again you know
and to be bringing shellfish and
and things up from the coast and sitting
down and camping there because
you know those the things that are
coming in from that you know into that
environment
is depending on us bringing those things
into it you know just in our cultural
practice
you know taking fish from the river and
eating it there i guess the same way
with the bears and the salmon you know
those forests need those salmon there
and the bears eating the salmon off in
the trees because
the trees have come to depend on what's
coming out of the salmon
you know it's the same thing yeah so i
always say like people tree huggers i
said don't
hug a tree like if you want to help piss
on the tree
you know the tree doesn't need your hugs
it needs your urine
you know um so do that all these
symbioses i keep coming back to it you
know i was thinking about the ticks
earlier
now they only get out of control and and
those parasites within them that create
lyme disease etc you know they only get
out of control when things are out of
balance
it's the same you know with all these
pathogens that are created
you know viruses are there for a reason
they have an evolutionary purpose
you know they help change things at the
genetic level
and they help to bring things in balance
with a constantly changing landscape you
know that's what they're there for
i did some work for uh a company and
basically what they did was they
they'd go whenever a big corporation was
shamed
over some terrible thing it did and
wanted to um improve its image
you know through philanthropic works
this company would go in and design
interventions that they could do in
third world countries to uh
sort of sharpen up their image a bit you
know put in a million dollars to help
this
and um yeah one company decided they
wanted to um
uh stop malaria in a particular place in
africa where you know the mosquitoes
were killing a lot of people
and um yeah i did some consulting for
that group ah
i really love the solution that that
came out in the end is
what they did was they fixed the river
so they um
they removed the dam that it that had
caused the river to slow and stagnate
you know and they they cleared the river
of all the rubbish and blockages and um
and caused it to flow
uh clean again and once the river was
flowing as it was supposed to
the mosquito problem was gone so rather
than ah how we gonna get
you know all these medications you know
into this community and
who's going to pay for it and all that
sort of stuff instead they just fixed
the river
and then they fixed the pathogen they
fixed the the health problem and the
malaria
and so it's you know it's all these
imbalances yeah you use that word a lot
and i think it
it should resonate for us if we're
starting to think about this idea of
custodial species
i'm going to play this back to you and
tell me if i'm full of or not is
that
uh you know the custodial species job is
actually to help
fine-tune the balance right to be a
helper in the domain of the complex
rather than a builder of the complicated
that tries to
dominate the complex yeah and you know
to adapt with change but then also
assist the system to transition in times
of change as well
yeah and i think that's a beautiful
thing you know it's some it's more than
a caretaker
a custodian is a it's a very deep
role and i think it's a it's a good
thing for people to think about meditate
on a little bit
you know you be surprised what might
fall out of that kind of thinking
a nice way to think of ourselves too
because i mean we're really
you know we're branding ourselves badly
human beings with
all our language and everything around
the anthropocene and
all this sort of stuff like it's caused
by human nature somehow
that's in our natures to destroy all
this but it's not us
doing it it's not our community
activities and
you know our way of life or anything
like that you know
communities are producing all of this
waste and toxicities it's the
big clunky tinkered complicated systems
you know that that have been sort of set
up around us
it's all these industries you know these
are the things that are using up all the
water and creating all the waste and
owning all this land and you know
locking it off and that's a terrible
thing
you know there's something like there's
only 20 of the habitat left on the
planet
and that is in dire trouble you know
because yes it's there's a lot of
toxicity going in and out of those
so they're not unpolluted but also in
those you know untouched wilderness
areas or you know natural places
you know they're kind of like these
islands of death because they're not
free to
exchange uncontaminated matter you know
across between different bioregions and
different systems
they're just kind of uh surrounded
pretty much like
i don't know the us military around
russia or something
you know yeah completely surrounded and
nothing can get in or out
and um yeah so you've got all these
national parks that are just slowly
dying
yeah and these things are driven by
systems upon system yeah you know at
least in my analysis
in the west the core system is this damn
money on money return
where the inner loop is
this drive to make money grow and in the
short term meaning less than three years
yeah and we have our businesses driven
by that we have our
you know frankly our family work you
know why do we need to have two
full-time people working 40 hours a week
to do what forager level people did two
to four hours a day one person yeah
actually
it's become a cultural thing too we're
we're all
speculating on our own individual
futures you know
we're we're all we're drawing on our
relationships in our time
and our you know and constantly building
our skills
and and all these kind of things you
know to speculate
on our personal futures and everybody is
this isolated individual
trying to do that so we're kind of we've
taken on this
ponzi scheme you know at the level of
the cultural dna
of our everyday lives you know we're
enacting that pattern
over and over and i guess that's that
horrendous uh you know narcissistic
pattern again
and it's having a feedback loop that is
really
uh manifesting itself in bad ways yeah
one of the things you talked about is
avatar depression
yeah talk about that for us that was a
very interesting idea
yeah i just it just makes me laugh that
one
it was like i was just trying to come up
with a theory as to why we had to wait
for
so long for a sequel to the first avatar
movie
you know and and i figured it was like
all these psychologists had to get the
medication
right to treat the avatar depression and
when i read the article on that i was
just laughed and laughed
that that's a real thing like it's a
real psychological it's a medical
condition
there's people who watch avatar and then
just give up on their life
because they see like they catch this
really
beautiful vision of a connected vibrant
existence you know completely immersed
you know in a landscape and a a culture
that has honor in it and
you know dignity and that they just they
see that and then they look at their own
life and they go ah
i don't want to do this anymore
and so they yeah there was this a lot of
a motivated people
and you know coming out of it and uh
yeah they had to try and figure out how
to treat it because it was millions of
people who were succumbing to it
i guess they had to get the medication
right before they released the sequel
and of course the third part you know we
have the beautiful blue people
you know we have our own society then we
also of course have
the theme of the movie which is the
mining monster
destroying the blue people yeah what the
are we doing right
i can see how that that could rock
people into a bad place yeah
trying to obtain the unobtainium yeah
unobtainium exactly yeah the rat race
yeah my friend brett weinstein recalls
this system
goliath right and it's not something
anybody controls that's the interesting
thing it's a meme
space entity meme in the dawkins sense
not in the
sense of a picture of a cat smoking a
cigarette yeah
but it it's a series of ideas and
signals
which are kind of like a standing like a
wave in a river the wave's always there
but the water flows through and
nobody actually made the wave it's an
emergent result of the action of the
water
so goliath is a emergent result
of our system of systems with at least
in my view money on money return at the
center
but fortunately because there is no one
in charge it means that if we can
change our systems in a major way we can
maybe make goliath be a lot less hideous
than he is today
yeah or just get your little sociopath
kid with a slingshot to
put a nice round rock between his eyes
exactly and there is one yeah called the
called the debt jubilee
right there oh yeah i believe we'll
bring down gold do you reckon that's
ever that's ever going to happen
a dead jubilee i don't know i've been
keeping that stone in my sling for a
number of years
uh and in fact there's a very cool
concept called the jubilee ratchet
yeah which makes it really work which is
that you threaten the jubilee
and if you think about debt there's an
interest there's two parts of interest
one is the time value of money right so
essentially the
call it the interest rate on a high
quality government bond
uh governments are getting a little
shakier but until recently he could call
it that
but the other is the risk of the
investment not getting repaid right so
a person who has bad credit they pay a
higher interest rate well guess what
if you start talking about the jubilee
and lots of people start talking about
it and investors start believing there's
at least a chance let's say it's only a
five percent chance
in the next five years that the jubilee
could happen
you know what that does that adds one
percent to the interest rate
for all loans yeah just talking about it
and that just talked it's called the
jubilee ratchet so yeah it's actually
probably the the biggest thing i have
ever invented in my life that you
believe
all you have to do all you have to do
mess with the economy is mess with
confidence
exactly and then suppose what happens
when it gets to 20
chance in five years that adds five
percent to the interest rate yeah and
what does that do it makes more people
want to have a jubilee to get this
goddamn monkey off their back
and that feeds back at a positive
feedback loop and eventually
beautifully i've done some simulations
on it and then when you get to the end
game it takes about six weeks to crush
the system oh my goodness
you you need uh yeah you need to deploy
that
not yet there's a i know but that
i talk about it's so funny i talk about
old man jumma fijo
in the book and and there's a rock
there's a sacred rock in a really secret
place
and he reckons if anybody ever touches
that rock like just puts their hand on
it
it'll be the end of the world it'll be a
cataclysm
and it's just every now and then you'll
be watching the news and you go and you
just
see a matter i might go touch that rock
i can understand i think you're sitting
on something similar there
but um yeah that would definitely do
some good
yeah yeah check out if you want to read
about the jubilee ratchet the early work
we did before game b was something
called the emancipation party
and the core of the emancipation party
was actually to deploy the jubilee
ratchet
it's written up in great and scary
detail
at emancipationparty.org so what the
hell i'm going to
sort of let it loose i'm not going to
deploy it oh my god yeah like
no but just let it sort of go out in
spore mode into the world and see what
happens
exactly it's just the idea itself you
know it's really interesting ideas five
years ago that were crazy like a ubi
nobody would countenance that five years
ago now
like people are considering it quite
seriously now yep
in fact our emancipation party had a uvi
in 2012 we called it the citizenship
wade yeah where every citizen would get
10 000
a year i think it was and every child
over four would get five
thousand the word ubi didn't even exist
but we invented it we thought it made
such obvious sense
yeah i'm gonna leap a little bit here
from you know the modern
and the tinkering and and
hacking with finance to
more indigenous ideas one of the things
that came up
again and again in the book and for me
was an eye-opener was the importance of
stone and rocks in your society in fact
i have a cool quote here this is from
max one of the people you talked about
stones to me are the objects that
parallel all life more so than trees or
mortal things
because stones are almost immortal they
know things learned over deep time
stones represent
earth tools and spirit it conveys
meaning through its use and through its
resilience to the elements at the same
time
it ages cracking and eroding as time
wears it down
but it's still there filled with energy
and spirit
yeah let's just wrap a little bit you
know a little on
stone in its importance and how
meaningful it is to your people
yeah it's really essential to everything
you know i i guess here's the thing in
any uh complex system
that there is self-organization that's
going on in that system
and so in in our way of looking at the
world
there's knowledge in that system that
that system has knowledge
and that all of its parts all the nodes
there they connect up
and they contain part of that knowledge
you know each node in the system
contains a part of that knowledge
every single entity and you know so a
being is not just a
human being you know there's also the
animals there's the plants
um but also you know a whirlwind or
you know a king tide or uh you know all
these kinds of things
that these are all things that contain
elements of the pattern in there which
is knowledge
and so from that point of view a rock
is sentient a rock contains knowledge
um a rock contains living spirit
and um yeah so therefore it's something
that needs to be treated with respect
especially because it's an
entity that lives for so long you can't
just
pick up a rock from anywhere and take it
home with you because the spirit of that
rock will you
don't know what the nature of that
spirit is you know so we have lots of
stories here
you know still now you sit around the
campfire if you're talking to somebody
you know there'll always be a story of a
family member they've
had who's uh done the wrong thing and
picked up a rock and taken it home
and ended up going crazy or dying or
getting tormented you know by spirits or
or something like this
you know so there's this idea of very
carefully approaching rocks and
utilizing rocks
and respecting them as things that
contain knowledge
and that are part of the system you know
and yeah they're constantly being cycled
you know through the earth and created
and recreated in the same way that we
are
and you know the trees that will lever
them up you know from deep down and they
bring up everything that we need for
life
you know phosphorus and all kinds of
things so yeah that's uh
i don't know that it's just this idea if
you're expanding the idea of what your
mind is and linking it out
you know moving if you you can
understand that haptic cognition and
recognize a tool as an extension of your
hand and that there's neural processes
going on in that
and then you can recognize that your
mind is actually going throughout your
body
that there's that awareness and then
that uh
yeah it's also going out into the tools
the other things that you're making with
that tool
so then you have an object that's
separate from you
and then you come to realize that well
the people
that you're in relation to that you're
carrying knowledge in that relationship
it's not just in that person's mind or
just in your mind
but the knowledge you create and share
together you're actually
sharing in a relational space between
you it's that
nora bateson's warm data i guess it's
like that
you know that the knowledge is in those
relationships yeah so you come to
understand all those nodes as containing
knowledge
but then you come to realize that that
that's not most of the knowledge
the most of the knowledge is in the
relationships between all the nodes
you know it's in these sort of invisible
lines of what we'd understand as spirit
that that goes throughout the system
like that and that is of course
the duality of reality we have objects
and we have relationships
and neither can exist by themselves and
you know
reductionist science and sort of the
more aberrant varieties of western
civilization
focus overly on the object and forget
the relationship yes
and yet without the relationships you
don't have anything yeah that's it
i could tell you a story about a
particularly sentient rock
do it i guess i've almost been
radicalized by that old man
juma fijo who i share a lot of his
symbols in the book that he wants to go
out to the
into the world to as many people as
possible because he believes it it'll
do this ritual action that'll change
people at the molecular level
and man i've even got jim rutz saying he
feels like his dna has been changed
after seeing these things
so that must be real there's a there's a
rock
out in a bay up uh darwin there
and there's a beacon that's been placed
on that so it's a steel beacon that's
been hammered into the rock
and um he says that's that's damaging
a lot of things just that beacon being
there it's blocking the work that that
rock does
for us you know so that rock is a
sentient part of that system
and you know the the tasks that that
rock does
can no longer be done because of that
beacon there and
so there's a blockage there of spirit
and one of the tasks that he's given me
to perform in my lifetime
is to somehow perform some kind of act
of domestic terrorism and remove that
beacon from that rock
and when i finally went out to that
place to see it i saw there's a military
base like right beside it on the shore
and i'm like oh man i'm not just going
to get arrested for this i'm going to
get
shot this is insane
terrible yeah so rocks are a really
important part like they're very large
rocks big geological features and
but the small ones as well they're a
very important part about cosmology
uh but see that's getting into the
spirit side of things jim
it's not your favorite uh that's not
your favorite business well it's
actually i love to talk about it right
but as you know i am so
if you you think of it as uh think of it
as just a different cultural metaphor
for a lot of the same things you're
talking about
yeah that's cool that and that that i
understand i'm very comfortable talking
about spirit but in
um you know that's why i i'm a novice
with complexity theory but i've
learned as many of the terms as i can so
that i can use those metaphors when i
speak to people
because that's uh people are from that
culture so i
want to respect them by using the
metaphors of their culture to talk about
you know we're talking about the same
thing
i'm talking about spirit but you know
you're talking about feedback loops
and you know we just have different
metaphors for those things
and information and patterns and things
like that there is one that maybe
integrates our views right you know in a
scientific valid
fashion do you know anything about julio
tonini's
integrated information theory oh no but
that sounds really good
uh this is very eerie stuff some of the
leading cognitive science working on the
problem of what is consciousness
kristoff coke
and julio tanini and james crick was
involved in it also for
a while francis craig whatever the crick
the one that's not watson from the dna
and they actually have a mathematical
formalism
called integrated information theory iit
it's usually known as
that all physical objects have
some level of consciousness and if you
could do the math which
today we cannot but we can approximate
it you can actually calculate the level
of consciousness
and he starts with an example of a light
switch and
says a light switch has approximately x
consciousness
right and a tv screen actually has not
very much consciousness but has a little
bit
right and guess what a rock has quite a
bit more a hell of a lot less than an
ant but it has some so tanini and his
collaborators have a mathematical
description
of consciousness in everything it's
basically an integration between
pan psychism and cognitive science
i would say it's well worth a look yeah
i know i definitely need to get that
yeah i'll send you a link uh when we're
done uh please yeah put it in the
i will say i'm i'm a little skeptical of
some of its implications but i do think
it's something we need to think about
and talk about right
yeah yes i famously complain about the s
word right
yeah yeah but it's not the concept i
think you know when i read your book i
at first said oh this is going to be
some moonshine and nonsense
says this right and i read it i
realized we're pretty much on the same
page
right yeah that it's about relationships
it's about
systems it's about patterns it's about
evolution
and it really isn't necessary in fact
you say somewhere in the book that you
don't have to believe in
ghosts right yeah and my form of
rejection of the s
word is the ghosts part the rest of it
i get and i appreciate and i appreciate
the fact that you explicitly called out
that it's possible to get this without
believing in ghosts
yeah absolutely you know and i mean you
can you know when i'm describing up the
four
our four parts of spirit you know i mean
you don't have to call it you know
what we call it in our various languages
or or even think of it like that
you can just quite easily have that idea
of lizard brain monkey brain
you know etc that way you know you could
use any any metaphor you like
look i'll talk to anybody because even
if the most insane ideas
you know they'll spark thinking in
different directions so i mean i love
talking to flat earthers
i love i love flat earthers so i get
some of my best ideas from flat earthers
their physics is you know
that you know your phone is not going to
work with with flat earth physics
they just they need to get some
physicists and work out the math
but then what a challenge what would
flat earth mathematics
be like what if you had to rearrange all
of the physics
and try and make those equations work
what if you had to just even attempting
that
impossible you know ridiculous you know
thought experiment
you might discover the next thing you
know it just might lead you off in a
different direction and you might find
the next thing so it's i mean it's
always good to talk to
different people and look at their ways
of viewing the world you're a better man
than i am
i got no problem with flat earthers they
get all the girls too
flat earthers and and if you want if you
want to
learn about networking you got to talk
to them because they seem to have a
down pat if they could sell that
they can sell anything right
yeah i mean they're doing it all on
machines that wouldn't work
if the world was actually flat but um
you know yeah they seem to
really have it down they certainly know
how to radicalize
otherwise sane people pretty quickly you
know i
wouldn't mind learning how to do that
well yeah the ability to sell
total horseshit it's quite a skill yeah
you did refute it with i thought was a
very elegant
example from physical realities as well
you know maybe i'll buy
uh flat earthism when somebody shows me
a flat
bubble yeah blow me a flat bubble i
don't know and of course
that shows an incredible knowledge
actually of physics and chemistry and
everything else right
that you know a bubble is what will be
formed as the most efficient in a
three-dimensional world
yeah that's it you know but then even in
just thinking about those ideas and
you know it just it occurred to me that
that would be a really good solution for
packaging you know if you could somehow
have round packaging
yep and you could get and get more
volume of stuff into a smaller um
object yeah a surface area minimizes the
amount of surface area and of course
that's one of the reasons we have cans
for things because they're halfway
between a square
and a sphere in terms of their
efficiency yeah on the flip side
they don't pack as well as squares so
there's tr everything is trade-offs
right everything's right
yeah that's it all right that's it we're
having a good time here chatting but
let's i want to hop ahead a little bit
skip over some of these other neat
little stories to some of the most
important i think part of your work that
i really make want to make sure it gets
out into the world
and one of them is that you have
identified a few simple operating
guidelines
sustainability agents basically your set
of diversify connect
interact and adapt i would really like
to spend a little bit of time
going over those four and your thoughts
about what they are
and why they're so important for a
sustainable agent or sustainability
agent that
you know is part of a system that needs
to be sustainable yeah
well i came to that by like just reading
about ai and i was thinking you know
about operating protocols and things
like that
and that it's always better to have one
that has a few simple
you know operating protocols and then
let it loose on a field of data
and so then i was thinking about all the
principles of complexity
um and all that sort of thing and i was
reading some
weird libertarian economist as well and
all those
kind of ideas converged and i thought
yeah it's just those four things
connectivity and that interaction uh
diversity also really important
but diversity i really like where
complexity theory took me with the
definition of diversity
as a principle because it's not this
kind of pc idea of just having
a few different colored faces around a
table you know
it's more than that diversity means
making sure you're as dissimilar as
possible
to the other nodes around you that are
similar to you
that's the first thing and and i found
that to be really important
you know that you can't just cluster
together in these groups where you're
all just
repeating each other's words these echo
chambers you see on twitter and
and you know in in cyberspace now
they're terrible because
you know everybody's just having this
group think but you need that diversity
where you're being
dissimilar from the people you're
similar to but then you also need to be
interacting constantly with
with other agents that are completely
dissimilar to you
and i was thinking about that in terms
of ecosystems and i was looking at that
and going yeah this is how all these
things
evolve all these symbioses you have to
have that
uh diversity and then that needs to be
the basis for your interaction
and you have to have a constant exchange
and you know of
energy resources matter you know between
all these nodes
so there was that and lots of different
connections
so in that for me that was very much
based on those pronouns
in our aboriginal languages that i was
talking about last week they lined up
really well with these things
all the different different kind of
connections you have to have
first of all the pairs you know that
there are pairs within a system things
that are paired together and then
there's exclusive groups and but then
there's bigger
you know inclusive groups and the entire
system as well
yeah i really like the way that worked
but then of course the most important
thing that all these lead to
and it's all for if you don't have
the last one but you have to have that
adaptivity
you have to be able to allow yourself to
be changed
a feedback loop needs to be transforming
you
you know if you're involved with it yeah
you can't be stagnating
at all you have to be adapting uh
constantly so you have to allow these
interactions and these exchanges of
energy to change you
and i guess that's the hardest part yeah
that comes from you know
very parallel to our complexity theories
concept of a complex
adaptive system right yeah that
truthfully
because the world is always in flux
around
us right the things outside of our
semi-permeable membrane
if we can't adapt in a to complexity
you know and in complexity and with
complexity
then we're not likely to be long for the
world yeah that's it
and you know i think i say in the book
that our elders
often say if you don't move with the
land the land will move you
you have to be at least as fluid as your
landscape and the things that are
happening within it
yeah and that's i think pretty much
exactly right and
exactly the same as the concept of
complex adaptive systems if you
are rigid the land is going to move or
the water is going to wash you away
right
yeah very you know a reed in a river in
flood is still there when the flood is
over but the bridge
is often gone right yeah and that's
that's very very very
important it strikes me i also wanted to
put another
connection between your work and other
work which i always find to be
interesting when i'm talking to people
when you talk about connectedness you
talk specifically about it starting with
pairs of people or pairs of anything
right yeah and
yeah there's a very interesting concept
called holarchy
from arthur kessler's book the ghost in
the machine
and the idea of a whole on is very
closely related which is that
and again with the conversation we had
earlier about relationships and objects
he makes them very interesting and
important and how the hell did we miss
it
western philosophy more or less missed
this is that
every object every holon as he would
call it is both an interior
and it's an exterior right so it is for
instance
a cell is interior of
a tissue or an organ but it's exterior
to the chemicals dancing around
inside of it you know a molecule is
interior to a cell but it's exterior to
the atoms that are inside of it
and you can go down at least quarks and
the philosophy there would say is
probably a bunch of levels below quarks
and we have no idea how high you can go
because like the human
is in a pair with a with say a spouse or
a best friend and
those people are in relationship with a
larger group and then
we were talking before the show about
hollow chain well guess where the hollow
comes from it comes from holarchy
so the hollow chain philosophy
is actually based upon
this idea of hollons and the fact that
everything is both an interior and an
exterior
depending on where it is in the emergent
relationships
yeah ah man and it's just the holochain
is such an elegant idea
you know if only that the clunky tech
would actually allow it
to be efficient it'll be amazing
yeah i did a podcast recently with art
brock
on the kind of nerdy technical details
of holochain
because i have fallen in love with it
yeah and we'll be doing another with him
soon
at a much higher level easier to
understand on
what hollow chain as a principle can let
us do with
especially with respect to things like
uh creating distributed currency yeah
we talked about the money on money
return machine you know the problem is
there's only one
signal make my money grow
right
yeah that's it and from that all the
sins of the world
almost not all but a bunch of them can
be derived but suppose there were
currencies for for instance the
preservation of that river you talked
about right
and anybody that up the river
loses that currency right
and anybody that makes that river
healthier gains that currency
and so the river has its own currency
yeah and so every action that's taken
that impacts the river
is signaled thumbs up or thumbs down by
the river currency
we could just take the chinese software
for social credits
and do ecological credits instead how
does that work
it's got to be decentralized it has to
be uh
adaptive no goddamn top down the chinese
are building the most complicated
society
ever yeah right uh they are
no surprise on the politburo i think uh
eight of the ten members are engineers
right not scientists but engineers yeah
and
so the chinese have decided to go all in
on complicated
they're gonna design it top down and
they're going to use brute force and
they're going to use murder and torture
and brainwashing
and everything else to have their way
and their social credit system
which initially sounds interesting i
believe is implemented by the way
they're doing it is a nightmare
it's you know
uh it's it's it's hard it's 1984
plus 1984 done right you know if you
were
if you were big brother uh you'd like to
have all the tools that the chinese have
at their
at their hands today well it's like
being it's like being
cancelled on twitter except you lose all
your money as well
yeah and your ability to travel and
probably your friends stop talking to
you and everything else
right all right so horrifying the worst
i mean
yeah you know when i talk about the bad
basins of attraction
in my essay in search of the fifth
attractor
i specifically lay out the chinese
neo-fascist is perhaps the worst that we
could fall into
yeah though it's a race between that and
fundamentalist religion in my opinion
both of them are pretty up
but something like holochain which would
allow
many competing signal currencies to be
adapted by people locally and if they
get adherents they start to do their
thing if they don't people just ignore
them then they go away
and that's the way it needs to be bottom
up and emergent not
top down and just crushing everybody's
soul yeah that's
it well i you know i mean you you did
say that
you know there is only one signal at the
moment and that's the money on money
return thing but
i think there's a lot of competing
signals starting to get out there
you know decentralizing um you know kind
of philosophies that are
and i think those signals are playing
quite well at the moment
i agree they're starting to yeah but
they're teeny teeny like our game b
theory or uh regenerative ecology people
like
joe brewer and daniel christian wall
these are very interesting and very
different ways of thinking about the
world but at least in terms of
at least in the advanced west i don't
think we're at point one percent yet
of impact on the system but the seeds
are there yeah which is the important
thing and from a little seed
a vast oak tree can grow yeah i think
you know most people would have heard a
bit bitcoin at least and
most people have heard blockchain and
they've heard these things and
you know and it's the ideas it's the
cultural ideas that start to seep into
people's
norms you know the more these
conversations are had and the more
interactions go on
you start to see people um starting to
just move towards this idea of
we don't need these bosses we don't need
these centralized authorities
and we need things better distributed
all of these systems truthfully i can go
on for hours and why i don't like
bitcoin and think it's actually worse
than
the current system energy intensive
thing is just
just so many bad things yeah run my
house for two years on the electricity
to make one bitcoin
anyway oh god the arguments we have in
my house about that you know
that sounds like that's my my woman's
doing a phd like i said earlier on them
to you on on bitcoin and indigenous no
not bitcoin blockchain and indigenous
knowledge
and um okay i'm not allowed to say the h
word which is holochain she gets wild
uh interesting now here's an interesting
quote
from your books i love that it actually
fits in exactly with what we just talked
about
which is this is actually your word the
most remarkable thing about western
civilization
is its ability to absorb any object or
idea
alter it sanitize it rebrand it and
market it
even ideas that are a threat can be
co-opted and put to work
the romans did it with christianity an
ideology of the poor and enslaved that
threatened the foundations of empire
when torture and murder became
ineffective as deterrence they simply
embraced the idea and made it the state
religion
maybe this ability of western
civilization more than any other
previous
civilization to adapt to anything might
actually be our salvation
yeah or maybe not but it seems to adapt
things
but it i mean it just adopts the
branding of the
things that's the problem you know it
takes the shell and throws everything
meaningful away
so it takes on the branding and the
labels of these things
and uh makes people feel happy that yeah
we're doing this
you know yeah we're i don't know
airbrushing all this with this
politically correct
language now but still the same systems
of imbalance and inequity and oppression
you know it's it's this this kind of
embracing of any idea that could uh
destroy the system and just taking on
the language of it and the images of it
and
turning it to support the status quo
though on the other hand
their things are like viruses right the
western
civilization has taken in as you pointed
out some of these radical ideas like
blockchain
yeah and it may eat it from inside yeah
well it'll it'll turn it it and it
already is
they're already turning blockchain into
something else they're finding ways to
like banks are embracing it and getting
on board with it and trying
to find ways to um you know the stock
market everything else
trying to find ways to incorporate it
into the money on money return
paradigm so they'll take it you know
and they'll go yeah decentralized but
they won't be
they won't actually do that they'll just
say they'll just call it that
but it'll still be the same ponzi scheme
just with a different name
running more efficiently right yeah like
the ibm
blockchain platform you know blockchain
for game a right yeah
and highly optimized and lots of
capabilities
but you know again the idea is now
loose one of my things that really
bothers me about having to raise the
consciousness of people
is that our monetary system in the west
did not come down from mount sinai with
moses right it was a series of frozen
accidents starting with the greeks and
you know
going through the establishment of the
bank of england in 1694 where we
for the first time had central banks
with fractional reserve currency you
know the federal reserve going off the
gold standard
this monetary system is not a given it
is a series of frozen accidents and we
can change it right and if we change the
monetary system
or have competing monetary systems then
that fundamental engine at the center
becomes a quite different beast
and it's possible that the west's
avidness to absorb any object or idea as
you put it
could well have it absorbed have may
already have absorbed
this virus of decentral bottoms up
self-organizing signals in a way that
may allow
the bottom to capture the top yeah
i wonder well i think that would be a
nice way to look at it
a nice hopeful note to end on but i
think usually it'll be
like dream catchers you know people like
to hang them off the
rear view mirror of their car or hang
them up around their houses
as decorations but they have no idea
about um
how those things are used in cultural
context in native american culture they
have no idea about the law and the
stories
around that they don't know about the
protocols
of that and and all of the social norms
attached to that and how you're supposed
to behave with those things
they just have them hanging on the wall
you know so they embrace the dream
catcher but they're still having the
same shitty dreams
and that's exactly right in fact in our
game b
discussion we use uh something so
similar it's uncanny
which is our biggest risk is that we
accidentally reinvent game a with
just game b terminology yeah well i
think you have a bigger risk which is
all the good stuff that you produce get
some stolen from you by
game a people who then call what they're
doing game b
and they use all your terminologies and
everything but basically um
use that to maintain their monopolies
yeah it's like green washing on
environmentalism right yeah and they
they
use some of your solutions to you know
be able to kick the can down the road a
bit further
yeah i'm sure people will try yeah well
tyson i
want to again say that your book is
the most meaningful book i have read in
years
and that's sand talk and i would
strongly encourage all people who want
to
try to reach towards what comes next
whether it's game b whether it's
something entirely else
to read this book and see if you can
feel it
in your dna trying to tell you something
i'm not yet sure what it's trying to
tell me but i know it's trying to tell
me something and
i'm going to be marinating on this
for some time to come and i certainly
look forward to talk to you again
just just let it work on you jimmy you
don't have to be even conscious of it
just
just keep going and doing what you're
doing it's it's magnificent and
beautiful
keep uh gaming the bee yeah exactly
it's working for me i'm loving it ah
great great chat with you and i look
forward to chatting with you
again in the not too distant future
sweet see you
[Music]
production services and audio editing by
jared janes consulting
music by tom muller at
modernspacemusic.com